Finding Aid for Detroit Area Study (University of Michigan) Records, 1951-2004
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Detroit Area Study (University of Michigan) records 1951-2004
University of Michigan. Detroit Area Study.
3.5 linear feet
0599 Bimu 2
The Detroit Area Study (DAS), conducted from 1951 to 2004, was a graduate training program in survey methods at the University of Michigan. Students conducted an annual survey in the Detroit Metropolitan Area (Oakland, Wayne, and Macomb counties), with a different research focus each year. Common topics included community life in an urban environment, family, politics, and race relations. The records consist of proposals, questionnaires, and analyses of the surveys.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The records were donated by the unit (Donor No. # #6039 ) in February 2005.
The record group is open without restriction.
The Detroit Area Study (DAS) project began in 1951. Initial funding came from the Ford Foundation, and continued, at least in part, until 1958. Afterward, the program was supported by the University of Michigan Department of Sociology. The program worked closely with the Survey Research Center, part of the University of Michigan Institute for Social Research.
The program was designed with three main goals: to facilitate faculty research, to provide students with practical training in survey methods, and to collect data which would be useful to the citizens of Detroit. The survey collected basic social science data, to allow for the study of trends over time, and data on specific research problems designed by the faculty of the university. The program was interdisciplinary, and included students from the departments of psychology, political science, economics, and the School of Social Work.
The DAS Executive Committee, composed of University of Michigan faculty, was responsible for choosing the topic for each year's study from faculty proposals. The member of the faculty whose proposal was accepted became the project director for that year, and was given five years of exclusive access to the data before it was made publicly available. Students enrolled in three courses: an introductory course on the survey topic in the fall, a course involved with designing and conducting the survey in the winter, and a course on analysis using the collected data the following fall. A typical study involved 300-500 interviews, 40-80% of which were conducted by the students. DAS project directors often obtained grant funding to increase the number of interviews in the sample. DAS served as a model for the development of similar programs at other universities, both nationally and internationally.
During the course of its existence, DAS had to frequently justify the expense of the program. In 1994, the DAS formed a partnership between the Department of Sociology, the Survey Research Center, and the College of LS&A to strengthen the program. The program was formally evaluated by the Department of Sociology in 1999-2000. The program was discontinued in Winter 2005, after the completion of the 2004 study.
Directors of the Detroit Area Study
1951-1953 Ronald Freedman
1954 Morris Axelrod
1955-1961 Harry Sharp
1962-1965 John C. Scott
1966-1969 Howard Schuman
1970 John C. Scott
1971 Howard Schuman
1972-1973 Bettye Eidson
1974-1975 Elwood Beck
1976 Howard Schuman
1976-1977 Robert M. Groves
1978-1980 David Goldberg
1981 Nancy Grassmick (Gebler)
1982 Peter V. Miller
1983-1985 Stanley Presser
1986-1988 Jean M. Converse
1989 Jacqueline Scott
1990 Karl Landis
1991-1996 Charlotte Steeh
1997-1999 Willard Rodgers
2000-2004 Mick P. Couper
The Detroit Area Study (DAS) records document a decades long survey research project focused on the Detroit metropolitan area. The records include administrative files documenting the development, funding and management of the project, publicity materials, photographs, publications produced by DAS staff or by others using DAS generated data, questionnaires and sampling reports the records are organized into four series: Administrative Files, Proposals, Questionnaires, and Sampling Reports.
Subjects:
University of Michigan. Detroit Area Study.; Public opinion--Michigan--Detroit.; Family life surveys--Michigan--Detroit.; Social surveys.; Detroit (Mich.)--Social conditions.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Sociology.; University of Michigan. Survey Research Center.; Inter-university Consortium for Political and Social Research.
- Administration
  Administration (1 linear foot, 1951-2004) includes correspondence, newspaper articles, photographs, and publications. The correspondence documents the daily administration of the program and negotiation for the continuation of the program. Of special note are letters from many former students written in 1974 about their experiences in the program. The newspaper articles are mainly publicity for the program, and discuss the purpose and findings of the projects. The photographs show students collecting and analyzing the survey data. Publications form half of this series. Some are published by DAS about the program, and others are publications by faculty and students using the data collected by the survey. Also of note are lists of survey topics by year and bibliographies of all the publications using DAS data. Publications are arranged alphabetically, by title.
  - Correspondence
    - Administrative 1974-1995 (Box 1)
    - Future of DAS 1974-2000, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Police Stop Student Researchers 1989 (Box 1)
    - Students Evaluate Their Experiences 1974 (Box 1)
  - Newspaper Articles
    - 1981-1990 (Box 1)
    - 1991-2002, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - History, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Press Releases 1952-1973 (Box 1)
  - Photographs
    - Students 1984 (Box 1)
    - Students (includes slides) 1986 (Box 1)
    - Students and Detroit buildings 1988 (Box 1)
    - Students and map of survey areas 1999 (Box 1)
  - Publications
    - Activities in Metropolitan Detroit by the University of Michigan (includes photographs of students) 1988 (Box 1)
    - Age and Environmentalism, by Paul Mohai and Ben Twight Social Science Quarterly, 1987 (Box 1)
    - Chronological Files
      - The Detroit Area Study, Original Statement of Objectives 1951 (Box 1)
      - The Detroit Area Study: A Training and Research Laboratory in the Community 1953 (Box 1)
      - Publications of the Detroit Area Study 1954 (Box 1)
      - Major Subject Areas Covered in Previous Surveys of the Detroit Area Study 1952-1954, 1954 (Box 1)
      - The Detroit Area Study Progress Report 1952-1954, 1954 (Box 1)
      - The Detroit Area Study 1951-1955 by Harry Sharp (first printed bibliography), 1955 (Box 1)
      - A Progress Report on the University of Michigan's Detroit Area Study 1951-1956, 1956 (Box 1)
      - Bibliography of Available Materials Based on Data Collected by the Detroit Area Study from September 1952-June 1959, 1959 (Box 1)
      - A Progress Report on the University of Michigan's Detroit Area Study September 1951-December 1959, 1959 (Box 1)
      - Bibliography of Materials Based on Detroit Area Study Research September 1951-December 1960, 1960 (Box 1)
      - The Detroit Area Study: A Review of Some Recent Research, by Harry Sharp 1960 (Box 1)
      - The Detroit Area Study: A Progress Report to the Ford Foundation 1960 (Box 1)
      - Graduate Training Through the Detroit Area Study, by Harry Sharp, reprinted from the American Sociological Review, 1961 (Box 1)
      - List of Detroit Area Study Student Analysis Reports 1952-1963, 1963 (Box 1)
      - The Detroit Area Study After Two Decades, by Howard Schuman 1969 (Box 1)
      - A Description and Bibliography of Materials Based on Detroit Area Study Research 1951-1969, 1969 (Box 1)
      - A Description and Bibliography of Materials Based on Detroit Area Study Research 1951-1976, 1976 (Box 1)
      - The Detroit Area Study After Twenty-Five Years, by Howard Schuman 1976 (Box 1)
      - Estimated Cost of the Detroit Area Study 1976 (Box 1)
      - Review of the Detroit Area Study Archives 1981 (Box 1)
      - Index to Questions Asked by the Detroit Area Study 1951-1975 (Box 1)
      - Summary of Respondent Characteristic and Response Rates 1953-1983, 1983 (Box 1)
      - Coding Reliability, Open Questions 1986 (Box 1)
      - Memo: Linking DAS to the Greater Detroit Community 1988 (Box 1)
      - Recent DAS Practice: A Memo to Prospective Investigators 1988 (Box 1)
      - A Record of Research Conducted by the Detroit Area Study 1951-1988, 1988 (Box 1)
      - On the Occasion of the Thirty-Seventh Detroit Area Study 1988 (Box 1)
    - Continued Racial Residential Segregation in Detroit 1993 (Box 1)
    - Detroit Area Study 1952-2001 Celebrating Fifty Years, 2002 (Box 1)
    - Detroit Area Study Conference 1980 (Box 1)
    - Detroit Area Study Listing Manual (Box 1)
    - Detroit Area Study Survey Topics 1951-2004 (Box 1)
    - D-R
      - The Detroit Area Study; A Brief Current Status Report, by A. Hermalin 1988 (Box 1)
      - The Detroit Area Study, ISR Bulletin 1997-1998 (Box 1)
      - Differential Incentives: Beliefs About Practices, Perceptions of Equity, and Effects on Survey Participation, by Eleanor Singer, Robert Groves, and Amy Corning 1999 (Box 1)
      - Dreher's Simplex Street and House Number Guide of the City of Detroit and Suburban Areas 1960-1962 edition (Box 1)
      - Fifth Annual Meeting of the Society for the Study of the Findings of the Detroit Area Study 1956 (Box 1)
      - I Am Not A Racist But ... Mapping White Racial Ideology in Post-Civil Rights Period 2001 (Box 1)
      - Public Concern and Elite Involvement in Environmental Issues, by Paul Mohai, Social Science Quarterly 1985 (Box 1)
      - Recent DAS Practice: A Memo to Prospective Investigators 1999 (Box 1)
      - Religion in Detroit 1958-1988 (Box 1)
    - Report To Respondents 1971-1977, 1981-1982, 1992-1995, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Separate and Unequal, The Racial Divide: Strategies for Reducing Political and Economic Inequalities in the Detroit Area 1989 (Box 2)
    - A Social Profile of Detroit 1952-1956 (Box 2)
    - S-Y
      - Some Aspects of Nonresponse in a Metropolitan Sample Survey by Ernest B. Attah, unpublished report undated (Box 2)
      - Statement of Professional Ethics, Survey Research Center 1980 (Box 2)
      - Study Fact Brochure: Detroit Area Study 1992 (Box 2)
      - Young White Adults: Did Racial Attitudes Change in the 1980s by Charlotte Steeh and Howard Schuman, 1992 (Box 2)
- Proposals
  Proposals (1960-2004, 0.25 linear feet) contain descriptions of the project proposed for each year, written by members of the faculty. Proposals are arranged chronologically, and not every year of the study is present.
  - Labor-and-Leisure Project and the plan for 1959-60 Detroit Area Study 1960 (Box 2)
  - Political Communication to the Union Worker: A Study of Primary and Secondary Group Influence in the Formation of Political Opinion 1961 (Box 2)
  - Factors Influencing Family Size 1962 (Box 2)
  - A Study of Family: School Relationships in Detroit 1963 (Box 2)
  - A Study of the Placement of Event in Time 1965 (Box 2)
  - The Structuring of Social Interaction in the Urban Community by Occupational Status, Ethnicity, and Kinship and its Impact on Selected Values, Attitudes, and Behavior 1966 (Box 2)
  - Citizens in Search of Justice 1967 (Box 2)
  - Careers in Detroit and Tokyo 1970 (Box 2)
  - Public Attitudes Toward Alternative Metropolitan Governmental Structures 1975 (Box 2)
  - Attitudes and Behavior, and Assessment of Responsibility and Punishment 1977 (Box 2)
  - Family Structure and Fertility: A Network Analysis of Behavior and Attitudes and Ethnic Effects 1978 (Box 2)
  - Crime and Crime Control in Detroit 1979 (Box 2)
  - Race, Class and Lifestage Differences in Male Family Roles and Family Relationships 1981 (Box 2)
  - The Stratification of Values: Social Inequality and Orientations to Children 1982 (Box 2)
  - The Public and the Welfare State: A Longitudinal Study 1983 (Box 2)
  - The Process of Mate Choice and Nuptuality in Detroit 1984 (Box 2)
  - Attributions of Intent and Judgments of Offense Seriousness 1986 (Box 2)
  - The Changing Role of Religion in American Society 1987 (Box 2)
  - Living Arrangements of the Frail Elderly 1988 (Box 2)
  - Political Participation 1989 (Box 2)
  - The Role of Race in the Siting of Hazardous Wastes 1990 (Box 2)
  - The Intersection of Personal and National History 1991 (Box 2)
  - Racial Division in the Detroit Area and the Causes of Racial Residential Segregation 1992 (Box 2)
  - Functional Health Status 1993 (Box 2)
  - The Role of Education in Sociological Explanation 1994 (Box 2)
  - Social Influences on Health: Stress, Racism and Health Protective Resources 1995 (Box 2)
  - Class, Race, and Space: Social Interaction in the City, and Survey Respondents' Reactions to Persuasion Attempts: Ethical Valuations and Behavioral Response 1996 (Box 2)
  - Social Change in Religion and Child-Rearing 1997 (Box 2)
  - Social Attitudes among Detroit Metropolitan Residents: An Exploration of White Racial Ideology in the Post-Civil Rights Era 1998 (Box 2)
  - Public Attitudes Toward End-of-Life Decisions 1999 (Box 2)
  - Impact of the 2000 Campaigns on Voters, 2000 (Box 2)
  - Assessing the Quality of Community Life and The Role of Environmental Quality in Explaining Socioeconomic and Racial Differences in Health 2001 (Box 2)
  - Understanding the Root Causes of Environmental Concern Domestically and Internationally 2002 (Box 2)
  - Local Responses to the Rise of the Network Society: Work and Consumer Participation, Social Networks, Beliefs and Identities 2003 (Box 2)
  - Social, Economic and Racial Change in Metropolitan Detroit 2004 (Box 2)
- Questionnaires
  Questionnaires (1952-2003, 2.25 linear feet) form the bulk of the records. The series contains the questionnaire used for each study. Most are blank, though a few surveys are filled out for 1953, 1958, and 1973. The series also includes supplemental material on the survey, such as correspondence, reports to respondents, evaluations of the effectiveness and accuracy of the survey, and analysis of the data. Common research topics included community life in an urban environment, family, politics, and race relations. The materials are arranged in chronological order.
  - A Study of Community Activities 1952, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - A Study of the Family 1953, 3 folders (Box 2)
  - A Community Study 1954, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - A Study of the Urban Family 1955, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - A Study of the Urban Community 1956, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - A Study of Political Participation 1957, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - A Study of Greater Detroit 1958, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - A Community Study of Greater Detroit 1959, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Labor-Leisure Project 1960, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - A Study of Workers 1961, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Family Growth in Detroit 1962 (Box 2)
  - Urban Families and Neighborhoods 1963 (Box 2)
  - A Study of Public Attitudes 1964, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - A Study of Urban Family Life 1965 (Box 2)
  - A Study of Attitudes and Relationships in the Detroit Area 1966, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Problems of Detroit Area Citizens 1967, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - A Study of Experiences and Problems in Detroit 1968, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - White Attitudes and Actions on Urban Problems 1969, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - A Comparative Study of America and Japan 1970, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Social Problems and Social Change in Detroit 1971, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Survey of Work Organizations 1972, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - A Study of the Civil-Military Interface and the Applications of Laboratory Methodologies in a Survey Setting 1973, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - A Study of Women's Labor Force Participation (includes codebook) 1974, 3 folders (Box 3)
  - Community Life and Politics 1975 (Box 3)
  - Metropolitan and Neighborhood Problems 1976 (Box 3)
  - Comparison of Telephone and Personal Interview Modes 1977, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - A Study of the Family 1978, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - A Study of Metropolitan Issues 1979, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Metropolitan Issues 1980 (Box 3)
  - A Study of the Family 1981, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Child Rearing Values and Practices 1982, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Attitudes and Experiences in Detroit 1983, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Marriage Customs and Family Life in the Detroit Area 1984 (Box 3)
  - Life Events in Everyday Experience 1985, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Social Change and Vignette Analyses 1986 (Box 3)
  - A Study of Greater Detroit 1987 (Box 3)
  - Perspectives on Care of the Elderly 1988 (Box 3)
  - Community Issues and Problems 1989 (Box 3)
  - Community and National Issues 1990 (Box 3)
  - Collective Memories 1991 (Box 3)
  - Social Change in Detroit 1992 (Box 3)
  - Study of Michigan Generations III 1993 (Box 3)
  - Social Attitudes 1994 (Box 4)
  - Health and Social Issues 1995 (Box 4)
  - Social Interaction and Survey Participation 1996 Social Change in Religion and Child Rearing, 1997 and White Racial Ideology, 1998 (Box 4)
  - Health Care and End of Life Decisions (includes materials from course on survey sampling) 1999 (Box 4)
  - Presidential Election 2000 Quality of Life, 2001 Understanding the Root Causes of Environmental Concerns, 2002 and Information and Values in Today's Society, 2003 (Box 4)
- Sampling Reports
  Sampling Reports (1971-2000, 0.25 linear feet) consists of evaluations of the accuracy of the data collected. The majority of the reports are from 1990 to 2000, with a few reports from the 1970s.
  - 1971 1976 (Box 4)
  - 1990-1991 (Box 4)
  - 1992 (Box 4)
  - 1994-1996 (Box 4)
  - 1998 2000 (Box 4)